Guide to the Records of the Office of the Chancellor/Executive Vice President (Borowitz) RG.6.0.7
New York University Archives
Records of the Office of the Chancellor/Executive Vice President (Sidney Borowitz)
1967-1977
1972-1977
New York University Archives
New York University. Office of the Chancellor and Executive Vice President
RG.6.0.7
35.75 Linear Feet 81 manuscript boxes and 1 oversize flat box
The Papers of Chancellor/Executive Vice President Sidney Borowitz include the materials generated during the years 1972-1977, and also include selected materials created in the Office of Chancellor Allan M. Cartter and elsewhere within the university community dating from as early as 1967. The papers have been divided into twelve series.
Separated Materials
Approximately 17.25 linear feet of material comprised of booklets, catalogs, pamphlets, personnel records, reports, sets of faculty and of Board of Trustees meeting minutes, and files (for some specifics see Scope and Content), were separated for containment elsewhere or, in the cases of personnel records or materials not germane to the University's history, were discarded.
Scope and Contents
These papers of Sidney Borowitz reflect the years he served as Chancellor/Executive Vice President of the University, 1972-1977. They include as well a small portion of papers formed during the Chancellorship of Allan M. Cartter, in particular Correspondence files created during the period beginning April 1971 and overlapping with Borowitz Correspondence files of May 1972. Additionally, the contents of one Paige box transferred to the University Archives in 1997 from the Office of Sponsored Programs were entered into this collection, augmenting material found in the Chancellor's files on the University Science Development Program initially funded at the University by the National Science Foundation in 1969.
This collection is composed of correspondence, memoranda, newspaper clippings, press releases, publications, and reports. As second in command, and deputy for the President in his absence, material was directed to Dr. Borowitz from throughout the University in connection with central administration decision-making and oversight requirements and responsibilities.
In consultation with the University Archivist, and in an effort to keep congruence between the Hester Papers (RG 3.0.7) and this collection, the Borowitz and previously noted Cartter Correspondence files were grouped as a subseries to the Borowitz Administration Series (Series 1), an alphabetical series combining elements comparable with Hester Series 1 (Alphabetical) and 2 (Administration). The remaining files were grouped into eleven categories (series), with most of the titles also found in the Hester Papers, in the following order: Associations; Development; Facilities and Services; Finances, incorporating Subseries I, Taskforce on the Financial Emergency, and Subseries II, University Heights Campus Disposition; Governance; Government Relations; Institutional Advancement; Personnel; Public Relations; Schools and Divisions; and Student Affairs.
The placement of like material does sometimes vary between series in the Hester and Borowitz papers. One instance is the location of documents concerned with the University's relationships with the New York State Department of Education; in the Hester papers these items are in the main found within the Governance Series, and in the Borowitz papers, in the Government Relations Series.
There is some overlap between content in Series 1 and the subsequent series'. Folder titles throughout reflect date and broad content subject matter. The impact of the aforementioned elements may occasionally be to slow the process of locating particular materials. Within limits, an attempt has been made mitigate this effect by providing cross-references where appropriate through notations on Separation Sheets filed preceding folder contents. Material is organized chronologically in folders, with a green plastic clip placed on the right margin of material highlighted in this Finding Aid.
As previously noted, and in some other instances as well, files were moved to bolster content clarity and consistency. About 8 inches of material of miscellaneous subject matter were found in folders labeled "Abeyance," the latter seemingly randomly packed into Paige boxes where there was space, in preparation for deposit in the Archives. These items were transferred to existing folders on the basis of subject.
Significant accumulations of materials concerned with matters already the subject of separately existing collections within the University Archives were removed and transferred to those collections, including Humanities Council materials (to RG 9.5.1), James Arthur Collection documents to the James Arthur Collection of Clocks and Watches (RG 42.1), Faculty Unionization effort (to Mss Collection RG 14 B1), and Jewish Culture Foundation materials (to RG 12.11).
A description of each of the Borowitz Papers series', with contents germane to major themes highlighted, precedes the Box and Folder list for that series.
Historical Note
At the time in the University's history that this collection was initiated, the Office of the Chancellor/Executive Vice President (C/EVP) held institutional responsibility as head of the faculty, sponsor of faculty appointment, termination and tenure, and chief liaison between faculty and students and the Board of Trustees. (1) Second in command to the President, the C/EVP exercised oversight over the schools and divisions as well as most internal organizational problems, with deans and officers reporting directly to him. (2)
Under President James M. Hester's leadership, the University by 1964 had embarked on an ambitious development plan to improve its facilities, raise its standards for admission, and increase its visibility within its urban community. (3) By the end of that decade, student protest, enrollment declines, and inflationary pressures were derailing those plans. It had become a time of financial difficulty for institutions of higher education throughout the country. (4) Recurrent and serious financial difficulties at New York University placed the continued existence of individual units at risk, and even threatened the future of the institution itself. When Sidney Borowitz became Chancellor in 1972, the University, regarded as the country's largest private institution, had been experiencing multi-million dollar annual losses. (5)
Dr. Borowitz, named acting Provost in 1971 of New York University's (NYU) University Heights campus in the Bronx, site of the University College of Arts and Science and the School of Engineering and Science, was appointed C/EVP May 1, 1972 by President Hester, 1962-1975, to succeed Allan M. Cartter, Chancellor 1966-1972. When, three years into Chancellor Borowitz' incumbency, President Hester stepped down, the Board of Trustees, after a national search, selected John C. Sawhill, 1975-1980, as the University's next president. During the early years of his time in office Dr. Sawhill seemingly concluded that he preferred "to operate without a Chancellor..." (6); Dr. Borowitz stepped down in 1977.
Temporary relief to the University's deficit in the early 1970's came with the sale brokered by the New York State Education Department (NYSED), of the University's Bronx campus, 1894-1973, to the City University of New York for use by Bronx Community College. Concurrent with discussions with officials in Albany concerning the future of the University Heights campus, President Hester convened a Taskforce on the Financial Emergency to address other questions related to the University's on-going fiscal problems; one member was the then Dean of University College Sidney Borowitz, Box 30, folder 5.
Under the terms of the final agreement with NYSED the University's School of Engineering and Science and its faculty were merged September 1, 1973 with the Polytechnic Institute of Brooklyn (PIB), and transferred to Brooklyn, effectively ending the University's long-term role in engineering education, 1854-1973. In a related move University College of Arts and Science and its faculty was merged with the Washington Square College of Arts and Science at Washington Square.
By the beginning of 1975 the University again faced major financial problems largely attributed to extreme national recession/inflation pressures, Box 4, folder 4. While Drs. Hester and Borowitz moved quickly to convene available members of the 1972 Task Force on the Financial Emergency, to review the University's current and projected deficit situation and recommend solutions, Box 2, folder 5, Dr. Hester's departure in effect transferred the initiative for resolution of these problems to his successor.
Also within its academic precincts, during this period the University experienced a faculty unionization drive, took some initial steps toward closing down its School of Social Work and then reversed itself, shut down its PhD program in Philosophy (FAS), not to be reinstated until the 1990s, considered closing the College of Dentistry or entering into a contract relationship with NYSED for its operation and support before its financial stability was assured through new understandings reached with NYSED, and created the Gallatin Division, expanded successor to the University School Without Walls program first recognized in 1972, and precursor of its current Gallatin School of Individualized Study, in tandem with a reorganization of the School of Continuing Education.
Among other institutional initiatives in that time, NYU established its initial policy and office responsible for Affirmative Action, broadened its governance machinery, undertook a major review of its mission and direction through a presidentially convened Goals Conference, and developed its Office of Student Affairs.
Dr. Borowitz was a member of the NYU physics faculty and taught at both the Bronx and Washington Square campuses. His wide acquaintance among faculty and administration at these university centers allowed him to consult broadly while maintaining the objectivity required by his role as a senior player in the resolution of situations demanding difficult decisions at the University and school levels.
1. Statues of New York University, January, 1989, pp. 3-4.
2. Baldridge, J. Victor. Power and Conflict in the University, New York: John Wiley & Sons, Inc., 1971, p.86.
3. The Mission of New York University, New York University Capital Program, 1964.
4. "100 Institutions Reported Facing Fiscal Disaster," The Chronicle of Higher Education, September 27, 1971, pp.1, 4.
5. "6 Private State University Heads Offer a Plan for State Action to Ease Rising Deficits," The New York Times, December 15, 1971, pp. 65, 68.
6. Sidney Borowitz to Reverend Joseph A. Lauritis, Duquesne University, March 23, 1977.
Conditions Governing Access
Institutional records of New York University are closed for a period of 20 years from the date of their creation (the date on which each document was written). Board of Trustees records are similarly closed for 35 years from the date of creation. The opening date for files spanning several years will be 20 years from the most recent date. Access will be given to material already 20 years old contained within a collection that is not yet open when such material can be isolated from the rest of the collection.
Materials related to personnel, faculty grievances, job searches and all files with information that falls under the University's Family Educational Rights and Privacy Act (FERPA) policy are permanently restricted.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Papers of Chancellor/Executive Vice President Sidney Borowitz were transferred to the University Archives after initial inventory in 1978. The accession number associated with this collection is 87.045.
Arrangement
Materials are arranged by subject in eight series: Series I: Administrative
Subseries I: Correspondence
Series II: Associations
Series III: Development
Series IV: Facilities and Services
Series V: Finances
Series VI: Governance
Series VII: Government Relations
Series VIII: Institutional Advancement
Series IX: Personnel
Series X: Public Relations
Series XI: Schools and Departments
Series XII: Student Activities
Correspondence.; Memorabilia.; Cartter, Allan Murray; Borowitz, Sidney, 1918-; New York University. Trustees; New York University. Finance Office; New York University. Financial Emergency; New York University -- Presidents; New York University. University Heights; New York University. Faculty of Arts and Science; Heald, Henry T. (Henry Townley), 1904-1975
- Series I: Administrative
  Scope and Contents
  These files, as noted previously, both are alphabetical and contain the Borowitz and accompanying Cartter Correspondence files as a subseries, Boxes 13 through 18. The series, largest of the collection, comprising 7.5 linear feet, offers what may be regarded as an overview of the Borowitz years. Some material is complementary to larger accumulations within subsequent series'. This will readily be observed in reviewing contents of Legislative Relations, Box 7, folder 11 through Box 8, folder 8, Federal Relations, Box 6, folders 812 in conjunction with those classified as Government Relations, Box 40, folder 11 through Box 46, folder 14. Contrarily, other material stands alone. Some examples are the folders labeled Appointment, Chancellor Borowitz, Box 3, folder 1 through Chancellor's Office, Administrative Advisory Committee, Box 3, folder 11, and Library, Box 8, folder 4 through Box 9, folder 9.
  Box 1 incorporates material relating to general academic and administrative matters. One notable instance is the topic of deans' review of vice presidential areas, folder 6. Box 2 contains Cartter testimony, 3/29/71, before the U.S. House of Representatives Education and Labor Subcommittee, sounding the alarm on the extent of financial difficulties within the higher education community, folder 12. Box 3 includes a copy of a report titled, "Effecting Economies in Higher Education," 8/73, addressing higher education's financial difficulties through the medium of case studies of New York University and Michigan State University (MSU), conducted by a MSU presidential staff member, folder 12.
  In Box 6, folder 4, there is a memorandum from Vice-President for Academic Planning and Services L. Jay Oliva to President Sawhill, 2/27/76, presenting a set of critical issues for institutional attention. Borowitz correspondence, Box 13, folder 16, contains views on the loss of the School of Engineering, and the effect of "past adversities" on (the University's) "destinies;" in Box 14, he addresses merger negotiations, folder 10, and relations with City College, folder 13.
  Other contents reflect Borowitz responsibility vis a vis the President's Office, other officers, schools and departments, and assorted initiatives under central administration purview. Box 17 offers some indication of the Borowitz personality and style, while Box 18, folders 1-7 provides a miscellany indicative of his working relationships with Dr. Hester and Dr. Sawhill.
  - Academic Matters, Feb 1974-Jan 1975 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    General note
    barcode: 3 1142 04224938 6
  - Academic Matters, Apr 1973-Aug 1973 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Academic Matters, Feb 1971-Mar 1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Academic Matters, Summer Session, Sep 1974-May 1976 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Academic Matters, Summer Session, Oct 1971-Jul 1974 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Academic Planning & Services, Office of, Oct 1974-Jun 1976 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Academic Planning & Services, Office of, Dec 1972-Jun 1974 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Academic Planning & Services, Staff Meetings: Minutes, Jul 1975-Apr 1976 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Academic Planning & Services, Misc, Feb 1975-Mar 1977 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Academic Planning & Services, Vice President for, Dec 1976-Jun 1977 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Academic Planning & Services, Vice President for, Sep 1976-Nov 1976 (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Academic Planning & Services, Vice President for, Sep 1975-Aug 1976 (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - Academic Resources, Mar 1975-Sep 1976 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Accountability, Aug 1976-Dec 1976 (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Administrative Services, Sep 1976-Mar 1977 (Box 2, Folder 1)
    barcode: 3 1142 04224939 4
  - Administrative Services, Sep 1972-Aug 1976 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Administrative Services, Sep 1971-Aug 1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Administrative Services, Feb 1970-Jul 1971 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Announcements, Sep 1973-Nov 1976 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Announcements, Apr 1971-Aug 1973 (Box 2, Folder 6)
  - Appointment Announcements, Sep 1971-Sep 1973 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Archivist, Mar 1973-Jun 1976 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Art Collection, including Grey Gallery, Sep 1972-Mar 1977 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Art Collection, including Grey Gallery Searches for Director, Nov 1973-Mar 1976 (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Awards, Alumni, et al., May 1973-May 1975 (Box 2, Folder 11)
  - Central Administration Views, Sep 1970-Dec 1972 (Box 2, Folder 12)
  - Chancellor, Appointment (Borowitz), May 1972-Sep 1975 (Box 3, Folder 1)
    barcode: 3 1142 04224940 2
  - Chancellor, Cartter Memorial, Oct 1976-Nov 1976 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Chancellor, Clippings, Misc, Mar 1974-Jun 1976 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Chancellor/Personal, Aug 1974-Apr 1977 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Chancellor/Personal, Harvard Board of Overseers, Visiting Committee, Mar 1976-Feb 1977 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Chancellor/Personal, Jewish Affairs, Jun 1972-Feb 1976 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Chancellor/Personal, Professional Activities & Associations, Jan 1976-Apr 1977 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Chancellor/Personal, Professional Activities & Associations, Jun 1972-Apr 1975 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Chancellor, Presentation to Council of Colleges of Arts and Sciences, National Association of State Universities and Land Grant Colleges (NASULGC), Nov 1972-Jan 1973 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Chancellor, Speeches, May 1972-Mar 1977 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Chancellor's Office, Administrative Advisory Committee, Jun 1973 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Chancellor's Office, Budget & Financial Matters, Dec 1972-May 1976 (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Chancellor's Office, Deans: Correspondence with All, Feb 1974-Apr 1976 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Chancellor's Office, Deans Meetings: Agendas, Minutes, Materials Distributed, Nov 1976-Dec 1976 (Box 3, Folder 14)
  - Chancellor's Office, Deans Meetings: Agendas, Minutes, Materials Distributed, Sep 1976-Oct 1976 (Box 3, Folder 15)
  - Chancellor's Office, Deans Meetings: Agendas, Minutes, Jul 1975-Aug 1976 (Box 3, Folder 16)
  - Chancellor's Office, Deans Meetings: Deans List of Faculty Titles, per Borowitz 11/26/75 Request, Dec 1975-Jan 1976 (Box 3, Folder 17)
  - Chancellor's Office, Deans Meetings: Materials Distributed, Mar 1976-May 1976 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    barcode: 3 1142 04224941 0
  - Chancellor's Office, Deans Meetings: Materials Distributed, Jan 1976-Feb 1976 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Chancellor's Office, Deans Meetings: Materials Distributed, Sep 1975-Dec 1975 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Chancellor's Office, Deans Meetings: Materials Distributed, Nov 1974-Feb 1975 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Chancellor's Office, Deans Meetings: Materials Distributed, Jan 1974-Oct 1974 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Chancellor's Office, Deans Meetings: Materials Distributed, Sep 1973-Dec 1973 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - Chancellor's Office, Deans Meetings: Schedules, Budget, Feb 1974-Jul 1974 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - Chancellor's Office, Deans Responses: Four Day Summer Work Week, Dec 1974-Mar 1976 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Chancellor's Office, Misc, Sep 1975-Apr 1977 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Chancellor's Office, Misc, Sep 1974-Aug 1975 (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Chancellor's Office, Misc, Sep 1973-Aug 1974 (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Chancellor's Office, Misc, Oct 1971-Aug 1973 (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Chancellor's Office, Reports & Questionnaires to Outside Institutions, Sep 1975-Feb 1977 (Box 5, Folder 1)
    barcode: 3 1142 04224942 8
  - Chancellor's Office, Reports & Questionnaires to Outside Institutions, Oct 1972-Jul 1975 (Box 5, Folder 2)
  - Committees & Panels, Misc, Oct 1973-Sep 1976 (Box 5, Folder 3)
  - Committees& Panels, Misc, 1969, Sep 1972-Aug 1973 (Box 5, Folder 4)
  - Consultants, Aug 1973-Jun 1975 (Box 5, Folder 5)
  - Contract Officer, Jul 1976-Mar 1977 (Box 5, Folder 6)
  - Contract Officer, Jan 1976-Jun 1976 (Box 5, Folder 7)
  - Contract Officer, Aug 1975-Dec 1975 (Box 5, Folder 8)
  - Contract Officer, Jan 1971-Jul 1975 (Box 5, Folder 9)
  - Cooper Union, Jan 1977-Mar 1977 (Box 6, Folder 1)
    barcode: 3 1142 04224943 6
  - Cooper Union, Nov 1976-Dec 1976 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Cooper Union, Feb 1972-Oct 1976 (Box 6, Folder 3)
  - Critical Issues, Feb 1976-May 1976 (Box 6, Folder 4)
  - Directories, President/Chancellor Offices, undated (Box 6, Folder 5)
  - Faculty Club, Jan 1973-Nov 1973 (Box 6, Folder 6)
  - Faculty Club, Jan 1971-Dec 1972 (Box 6, Folder 7)
  - Federal Relations, Jan 1976-Jun 1976 (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Federal Relations, Sep 1975-Dec 1975 (Box 6, Folder 9)
  - Federal Relations, Feb 1975-Aug 1975 (Box 6, Folder 10)
  - Federal Relations, Jul 1973-Jan 1975 (Box 6, Folder 11)
  - Federal Relations, Jul 1972-May 1973 (Box 6, Folder 12)
  - Hall of Fame, Nov 1973-Nov 1976 (Box 6, Folder 13)
  - Hall of Fame, Nov 1971-Aug 1973 (Box 6, Folder 14)
  - Hebrew and Jewish Studies, Center for; Hebrew Union College, 1976-Mar 1977, Dec 1971-Mar 1977 (Box 6, Folder 15)
  - Information Systems Planning Study, Identification Phase Report, Nov 1976 (Box 7, Folder 1)
    barcode: 3 1142 04224944 4
  - Information Systems Planning Study, Jul 1974-Sep 1976 (Box 7, Folder 2)
  - Institutional Research & Planning, Sep 1975-Feb 1976 (Box 7, Folder 3)
  - Institutional Research & Planning, Feb 1974-Jun 1975 (Box 7, Folder 4)
  - Institutional Research, Office of, Oct 1971-Mar 1973 (Box 7, Folder 5)
  - Legal Counsel, Office of, Oct 1975-Feb 1977 (Box 7, Folder 6)
  - Legal Counsel, Office of, Oct 1973-Jun 1975 (Box 7, Folder 7)
  - Legal Counsel, Office of, Aug 1973 (Box 7, Folder 8)
  - Legal Counsel, Office of, Jul 1973 (Box 7, Folder 9)
  - Legal Opinions, Sep 1974-Jul 1975 (Box 7, Folder 10)
  - Legislative Relations, Memos, Bills, Oct 1976-Apr 1977 (Box 7, Folder 11)
  - Legislative Relations, Memos, Bills, Jun 1976-Sep 1976 (Box 7, Folder 12)
  - Legislative Relations, Memos, Bills, Feb 1976-May 1976 (Box 7, Folder 13)
  - Legislative Relations, Memos, Bills, Sep 1975-Jan 1976 (Box 7, Folder 14)
  - Legislative Relations, Memos, Bills, Apr 1975-Aug 1975 (Box 8, Folder 1)
    barcode: 3 1142 04224945 1
  - Legislative Relations, Memos, Bills, Sep 1974-Mar 1975 (Box 8, Folder 2)
  - Legislative Relations, Memos, Bills, Nov 1971-Aug 1974 (Box 8, Folder 3)
  - Library, Sep 1976-Feb 1977 (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Library, Jul 1976-Aug 1976 (Box 8, Folder 5)
  - Library, Mar 1976-Jun 1976 (Box 8, Folder 6)
  - Library, Jan 1976-Feb 1976 (Box 8, Folder 7)
  - Library, Sep 1975-Dec 1975 (Box 8, Folder 8)
  - Library, May 1975-Aug 1975 (Box 9, Folder 1)
    barcode: 3 1142 04224946 9
  - Library, Sep 1974-Apr 1975 (Box 9, Folder 2)
  - Library, Feb 1974-Aug 1974 (Box 9, Folder 3)
  - Library, Sep 1973-Jan 1974 (Box 9, Folder 4)
  - Library, Oct 1970-Aug 1973 (Box 9, Folder 5)
  - Library, Budget & Financial Matters, Jan 1974-Dec 1976 (Box 9, Folder 6)
  - Library, Minutes of Meetings, Mar 1971-Dec 1974 (Box 9, Folder 7)
  - Library, Search for Dean, Jun 1975-Jul 1976 (Box 9, Folder 8)
  - Library, Study by Dean Robert B. Downs, Jul 1974-Nov 1974 (Box 9, Folder 9)
  - Lists, Administration, Jun 1972-Sep 1975 (Box 10, Folder 1)
    barcode: 3 1142 04224947 7
  - Lists, Faculty, Aug 1975-Jan 1976 (Box 10, Folder 2)
  - Lists, Faculty, Sep 1973-Dec 1973 (Box 10, Folder 3)
  - Lists, President/Chancellor Luncheons: Faculty and Administrators, Sep 1974-May 1975 (Box 10, Folder 4)